Zionism Collection 0011.003.003
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Zionism
Bulk, 1940-1960
1912-1997
0011.003.003
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
8.0 Cubic feet 10 regular boxes, 2 quarter-size boxes, 1 oversized box
This collection consists of manuscripts, artifacts, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, photos, and other ephemera and memorabilia documenting the Zionist organizations and activities associated with the Greater Hartford area. Like many Jewish communities, Hartford's Jews were concerned with the conditions facing their co-religionists worldwide. They supported many causes dedicated to relieving this suffering and immediately rallied behind Theodor Herzl, whose book The Jewish State [Der Judenstaat], written in 1894, called for the creation of an internationally recognized and guaranteed home for the Jewish people in Palestine. Herzl, a jounalist, was shocked by the virulent anti-Semitism he witnessed during the Dreyfus trial in France, and the book expressed his view that the only long-term and permanent solution to anti-Semitism was a Jewish homeland. After 1897, when the first Jewish Congress met in Basel, Switzerland, the Zionist movement began to take shape in America. In Hartford that year, a handful of enthusiastic and far-seeing Jews organized the B'nai Zion Society, and this organization soon became one of the staunch pillars of the Zionist movement in this country. In the course of the development of the Zionist movement, many national and international Zionist figures visited and addressed public meetings in Hartford. Among them were Dr. Shemaryahu Levin, a member of the former Russian Duma ( parliament ) who, when it was dissolved in 1905, had been forced to leave his native land; Naftali Imber, composer of the "Hatikvah," the national anthem of Israel; the renowned author and humorist, Sholom Aleichem; the Hebrew writer, Reuben Brainin; Hayim Nahman Bialik, the national Hebrew poet; Nahum Sokolow, noted scholar and linguist, and former president of the World Zionist Congress; Ittamar Ben Avi, Hebrew journalist; Rabbi Meyer Berlin ( Bar Ilan), leader of World Mizrachi; Louis Lipsky, renowned Zionist leader; Professor Israel Friedlaender of the Jewish Theological Seminary; Dr. Judah Magnes, later president of the Hebrew University; Professor Horace M. Kallen; Hirsch Masliansky, prominent Yiddish orator; Joseph Barondess, labor leader; Abe Goldberg, Yiddish journalist; Justice Louis D. Brandeis; Rabbi Stephen S. Wise; Zev Jabotinsky, revisionist leader; Henrietta Szold, founder of Hadassah; Golda Meyerson ( Meir ), founder of the Pioneer Women; Emanuel Neuman, Zionist leader; Dr. Nahum Goldman, president of the World Jewish Congress; and Professor Albert Einstein. Chaim Weizmann, president of the World Zionist Congress, and later first president of the State of Israel, frequently visited Hartford. During the Nazi regime, Hartford's Zionist committees frequently went to Washington to plead with the State Department and members of Congress to persuade the British Mandate authority to open the doors of Palestine to Jewish victims of the Nazis. A few years later on May 14,1948, Hartford Jews, along with Zionists throughout the world, rejoiced when the State of Israel was declared by the provisional government in Palestine and immediately recognized by U.S. President Harry Truman.
Related Archival Materials note
Related JHSGH Collections:
Zionism Subject collection
Samuel Hoffenberg collection
Abraham Goldstein collection
Zionist Organization of America collection
Farband Labor Zionist Order collection
Ben-Guiron, David, Politician, Prime Minister, 1886-1973, Plonsk, Poland; Berman, Saul, Judge, Honorable; Brandeis, Louis D., 11/13/1856 - 10/05/1941, Louisville, KY; Dunn, Morris S.; Einstein, Albert, Physicist, Germany; Gans; Gaster, Berthold, Journalist/The Ledger, b.1926, Vienna; Goldstein, Abraham, Insurance, 12/30/1893 - 11/16/1953, Kiev, Russia; Herzl, Theodor, 05/02/1860-07/03/1904, Hungary; Hoffenberg, Samuel, Insurance Broker, 1892-1987, Asvolink, Lithuania (Kovna); Klau, Joseph E., Law, Judge; Kleinman, Harry, b.1908, Chestnut Street, Hartford, Connecticut; Kone, Samuel C., Real Estate broker, 10/18/1880-02/02/1951, Russia; Meir, Golda, Politician, Teacher, Prime Minister, b.1878/5/3 d.1978/12/8; Meltzer, Irving; Neumann, Emanuel; Okolica, Henry, Rabbi, Germany; Plen, Sarah Marder; Rivkin, Samuel; Schwolsky, Jacob, Judge; Sheketoff, Louis; Shulman, Paul; Silver, Abba Hillel, Rabbi; Tabatsky, Abraham; Tulin, Abraham; Weizmann, Chaim, Doctor; Wingate, Orde; Wise, Stephen S., Rabbi; Zeldis, Louis, 12/4/1900, Lokshivka, Ukraine, Russia; Zucker, Libbe Dunn; American Friends of Hebrew University, CT Chapter; American Red Magen David; American Technion Society; American Zionist Council; American Zionist Movement; American Zionist Youth Federation; American-Israeli Relations; Arab Refugees; B'nai Zion; Black Paper; Blood Libel; Brandeis Banner; Camp David Accords; Connecticut State Zionist Association; Haganah; Hartford Zionist Choral Group; Hashhomer Hatzair Archives; Herut Zionists; Histadrut; Israel; Israel Bonds; Jewish Frontier; Jewish National Fund of Greater Hartford, Keren Kayemeth; Junior Keren Hayesod; Labor Zionism; Maccabean; Maps; Mizrachi; Palestine; Pioneer Women; Postcards; Religious Zionists of America; Six Day War, 1967; Social Welfare; United States-Middle East Policy; United Zionists; Women's American ORT; Yom Kippur War, 1973; Young Judaean Magazine; Youths of Zion; Zionism; Zionist Emergency Council
- Series I: Small Series
  - Zionism/ Aliyah/ Local Residents, undated
  - Zionism/ American Veterans of Israel, undated
  - Zionism/ Anti-Zionism, undated
  - Zionism/ "Brandeis Banner", 1944
  - Zionism/ Correspondence, undated
  - Zionism/ Camp David Accord/ Newspapers, undated
  - Zionism/ Connecticut Colony in Israel, undated
  - Zionism/ Creation of the State of Israel/ Local Reaction, 1948, undated
  - Zionism/ Connecticut-Israel Business Relations, undated
  - Zionism/ Emmigrants to Israel from Hartford, CT, undated
  - Zionism/ Documents, Miscellaneous 1900-1940s, 1900-1949
  - Zionism/ Fundraising, undated
  - Zionism/ Haganah, undated
  - Zionism/ Hashomer Hatzair Archives, undated
  - Zionism/ Historical Overviews and Reference, undated
  - Zionism/ Israeli Bond, undated
  - Zionism/ Israel Independence Day Celebrations, undated
  - Zionism/ Israeli Military Service by Local Residents, undated
  - Zionism/ "Hartford's Role in the Birth of Israel"/ Transcript of interview with Judge Joseph Klau and Attorney Harry Kleinman, undated
  - Zionism/ Labor Zionism, undated
  - Zionism/ Literature, undated
  - Zionism/ Maps [including 1924 motorist tour map]
  - Zionism/ Miscellaneous, undated
  - Zionism/ New Britian, undated
  - Zionism/ Habonim Newletters 1940s
  - Zionism/ "Peace for Galilee Operation" and African Friends of Israel, Incorporated, undated
  - Zionism/ Photocopies from articles and books, undated
  - Zionism/ Photocopies of documents in other JHSGH collections, undated
  - Zionism/ Photocopies of JHSGH exhibit panels, undated
  - Zionism/ Public Opinion Re: Israel, undated
  - Zionism/ Religious Zionists of America, undated
  - Zionism/ Six Day War, undated
  - Zionism/ World Jewry 1945-1946/ Demographic Records
  - Zionism/ Yom Hazikaron Commemorations, undated
  - Zionism/ Yom Kippur War, undated
  - Zionism/ Yom Kippur War, 1973, Local Response
  - Zionism/ Youth Tours & Study in Israel, undated
  - Zionism/ Zionist Convention, New York, undated
- Series II: Ephemera
  - Zionism/ Ephemera/ Commemorative, undated
  - Zionism/ Ephemera/ Miscellaneous, undated
  - Zionism/ Ephemera/ Postcards - Israel, undated
- Series III: Newspaper Clippings
  - Zionism/ Newspaper Clippings/ 1920s, 1920-1929
  - Zionism/ Newspaper Clippings/ 1930s, 1930-1939
  - Zionism/ Newspaper Clippings/ 1940s, 1940-1949
  - Zionism/ Newspaper Clippings/ 1950s, 1950-1959
  - Zionism/ Newspaper Clippings/ 1960s, 1960-1969
  - Zionism/ Newspaper Clippings/ 1970s, 1970-1979
  - Zionism/ Newspaper Clippings/ 1980s, 1980-1989
  - Zionism/ Newspaper Clippings/ 1990s, 1990-1999
- Series IV: Local Zionist Organizations
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ American Friends of Hebrew University, CT Chapter, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ American Red Magen David, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ American Technion Society, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ American Zionist Council, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ American Zionist Youth Federation, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ B'nai Zion, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Connecticut State Zionist Association, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Hartford Committee for the Jewish Pioneers in Palestine [Mortesen letter and pamphlet -- missing], undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Hartford Zionist Choral Group, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Herut Zionists of America, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Israeli Histadrut Committee, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Israel's Welfare and Security [Mizrachi Women Chapter telegram to Richard M. Nixon], undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Jewish National Fund of Greater Hartford ("Keren Kayemeth"), undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Junior Keren Hayesod, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ League for Labor Palestine, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ O.R.T., Women's American [Organization for Rehabilitation Through Training], undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Maccabaeans, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ United Zionists, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Young Judaea Association of Connecticut, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Youths of Zion, undated
  - Zionism/ Local Zionist Organizations/ Zionist Emergency Council, undated
- Series V: Anniversaries
  - Zionism/ Anniversaries/ Independence Day, 1948
  - Zionism/ Anniversaries/ 10th Year Independence 1958
  - Zionism/ Anniversaries/ 25th Year Independence, 1973
  - Zionism/ Anniversaries/ 35th Year Independence, 1983
  - Zionism/ Anniversaries/ 40th Year Independence, 1988
  - Zionism/ Anniversaries/ 50th Year Independence, 1998
  - Zionism/ Anniversaries/ Zionist Movement 60th Year, 1978
  - Zionism/ Anniversaries/ Zionist Movement 100th Year, 1997
- Series VI: People A-L
  - Zionism/ People A-L/ Ben-Guiron, David, undated
  - Zionism/ People A-L/ Brandeis, Louis B., undated
  - Zionism/ People A-L/ Gans Family, undated
  - Zionism/ People A-L/ Herzl, Theodore, undated
- Series VII: People M-Z
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Meir, Golda, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Israeli Military Service by Local Residents/ Meltzer, Irving, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Israeli Military Service by Local Residents/ Sarah Marder Plen [also see Oral History collection], undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Neumann, Emanuel, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Okolica, Henry, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Shulman, Paul, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Silver, Rabbi Abba Hillel, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Tabatsky, Abraham, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Tulin, Abraham, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Weizmann, Chaim, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Weizmann and Einstein Visit Hartford, 1921, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Weizmann Memorial Observance, 1952, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Wingate, Orde, undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Wise, Rabbi Stephen S., undated
  - Zionism/ People M-Z/ Zucker, Libbe Dunn, undated
- Series VIII: Pamphlets, A-I
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Absorptive Capacity of Palestine, The (1943), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Afula [in Hebrew], undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ American Mercury, The (1943)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ American Palestine Committee (1943)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ America Speaks: A Legend is Born (1976), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Arnold Toynbee and the Jews (1955)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Biblical Explorer By Land and Air (1955), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Black Paper: The British Terror in Palestine, undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Brief for Action: Issued by the League of Women Voters (April 2, 1948), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Education in Israel: A Survey (1963-1964)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Facts and Figures: Israel (1956)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ False Witness: The Record of the American Council for Judaism (1955), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Founding of Two Nations: Israel and the United States, The (1954), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Freedom from Intimidation (1928)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ The Future of the Arab Refugees (1954), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Hard Questions and Answers on the Middle East (1968), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Histadrut: Makers of History by Moshe Sharett (1959), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ In the Dispersion, issued by the World Zionist Organization, 2 volumes (1962), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Israel Among the Nations by David Ben-Guiron (1952), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Israel and the Arab States: The Issues in Dispute (1951), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Israel Explodes Dir Yassin Blood Libel, undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Israel Reborn (1950)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Israel Strikes at Bases of Egyptian Aggression; Acts in Self-Defense by Abba Eban (1956), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Israel Reborn, an album edited by I. Klinov, undated
- Series IX: J-Z
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Jewish Agency Before the United Nations (1947), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ The Jewish Case: The Place of Palestine in the Solution of the Jewish Question, undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Jewish Frontier (October, 1977)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Jewish Frontier (November, 1949)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Jewish National Fund/ Land and Life (1978), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ The Jewish Problem, by Louis D. Brandeis (1934), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Joint Distribution Committee Album, The (1914-1954), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Nature of the Jewish Problem, The (1943), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ New Directions for Zionism (1958)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ No Retreat! (1967), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Our Voice: Israel Today (1972)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ [A] Palestine Solution by Andrei Gromyko (1947), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Palestinian Messengers in America, 1849-1979 (1943), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ [A] Proposal for An International Curatorship for the Holy Places, undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Record of Aggression, The 1958-1967 (1967), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Social Welfare (1965)
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ State of Israel/ Facts and Figures (1954), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Today Ford Attacks the Jews, Why?, undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ United States Middle-East Policy: Peace or Appeasement (1970), undated
  - Zionism/ Pamphlets/ Young Judaean Magazine (1923)
- Series X: Quarter Box 1 -- Zionism/ JHSGH/ Publication Mock-Up
- Series XI: Quarter Box 2 -- Miscellaneous Folders
  - Zionism/ Miscellaneous Folders/ Waterbury Zionism, undated
  - Zionism/ Miscellaneous Folders/ WPA, undated
  - Zionism/ Miscellaneous Folders/ Young People's League, undated
  - Zionism/ Miscellaneous Folders/ Zionism (Dalin), undated
  - Zionism/ Miscellaneous Folders/ Zionism Karen Hayesod, undated
  - Oversized Box: contains certificates, news magazines, photographs, undated